Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1861-1864
      - March 11, 1863 - March 17, 1863 (Box 22, Folder 15)
        Cornell, D.B.; Tarbell, D.; Schuyler, G.W.; Terrey, D.; Curtiss, George; Pew, W.P.; Cornell, E.B.; Chester, E.W.
      - March 18, 1863 - March 25, 1863 (Box 22, Folder 16)
        New York State Legislature: letters from constituents; Forest Park farm; cattle; Cornell Public Library; Western Union Telegraph Company; land grant appropriations; response to address before the New York State Agricultural Society.
        Cornell, Franklin C.; Van Rensselaer, R.H.; Mumford, G.H.; Curd, John; Chace, Miller; Curtiss, George; Finch, F.M.; King, J.H.; Wood, W. Irving; Macy, Philander; Glenny, G.
      - March 26, 1863 - April 6, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence; Land Grant Act; New York State Legislature: legislation; Cornell Public Library; Family correspondence; Danby farm; Civil War; Montreal Telegraph Company.
        April, 1863:
        "Received of E. Cornell seventy three dollars for support of families of Colored Volunteers of Albany County."
        Pew, W.P.; Wood, O.S.; Curtiss, George; Finch, F.M.; Cornell, O.H. Perry; Torrey, William A.; Cornell, Franklin C.
      - April 7, 1863 - April 13, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 2)
        New York State Legislature: legislation; Copperheads; cattle; Sodus Canal; Cornell Public Library; coal oil business; Land Grant Act; Cayuga and Oswego Canal.
        Pew, W.P.; Wood, M.B.; Finch, F.M.; Schuyler, A.; Curtiss, George.
      - April 14, 1863 - April 29, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 3)
        New York State Legislature: legislation; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends; Land Grant Act; People's College (Havana); Wisconsin lands.
        April 16, 1863. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from encampment in the Union Army.
        April 17, 1863. M.B. Wood to Ezra Cornell:
        "We are watching with great anxiety to hear of Charleston being taken by our forces and are preparing for a big jollification on receipt of the news. We have a big national flag ready to raise that cost us $36 in NY city."
        Pew, W.P.; Finch, F.M.; Cornell, D.B.; Chester, E.W.
      - May 1, 1863 - May 18, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 4)
        New York State Agricultural College (Ovid); New York State Agricultural survey; New York State Canal Commissioner's Office; Loyal League of Union Citizens; Civil War; agriculture; Western Union Telegraph Company.
        May 1, 1863. W.O. Wyckoff to Ezra Cornell describing life in the Union Army.
        Pew, W.P.; Chester, E.W.; Wood, M.W.; Curtiss, George.
      - May 19, 1863 - June 28, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 5)
        Agriculture; Cornell Public Library; Civil War; cattle; Cornell family genealogy and history; New York State Bureau of Military Statistics; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends.
        May 24, 1863. W.O. Wyckoff to Ezra Cornell describing life in the Union Army.
        DeRuyter.
        Sibley, Hiram; Wood, O.S.; Wood, M.W.; Wyckoff, W.O.; Barnard, D.R.; Cornell, Paul J.; Pew, W.P.; Carpenter, Eber.
      - July 2, 1863 - July 28, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 6)
        New York State Legislature: letters from constituents; Western Union Telegraph Company: stock.
        Pew, W.P.; Wood, Daniel; Curtiss, George.
      - August 1, 1863 - September 7, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 7)
        Agriculture; Civil War; Cornell Public Library; New York State Agricultural Rooms; telegraph industry; Sodus Canal.
        August 3, 1863. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell including a meticulous account of his participation in the Battle of Vicksburg and his near fatal injury suffered in the assault:
        "I received my wound on the 19th of May at the first charge on the works in the rear of Vicksburg, our Brigade charged on what was called Fort Hill. ?my position was colour bearer and I had to go down a small ravine which was in the hillside?I was struck directly under and about 3/4 of an inch from my left eye --I did not fall, nor did the colours go down?I then went and lay down behind a fallen tree expecting to bleed to death?the ball had apparently struck the limb of a tree and was comeing diagonaly down as it passed through my hat rim over my left temple, it passed through the roof of my mouth cutting an ugly gash on the inside of my right cheek and lodged at the angle of my jaw shattering it severely."
        Kansas; Vicksburg, Ms.; Albany.
        Pew, W.P.; Cornell, D.B.; Wood, O.S.; Chace, Miller; Chester, E.W.
      - September 8, 1863 - September 28, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 8)
        Agriculture; cattle; Cornell Public Library; New York State Agricultural Rooms; New York State Legislature; Ezra Cornell's election to the State Senate; Ezra Cornell's charitable contributions.
        Kansas; Albany.
        Millspaugh, John H.; Cornell, E.S.; Pew, W.P.; Wood, O.S.
      - September 29, 1863 - October 10, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 9)
        New York State Legislature: letters from constituents; Agriculture; New York State canals; cattle.
        October 2, 1863. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing life in a convalescent hospital in Illinois.
        Wells, Henry; Chester, George F.; Cornell, D.B.
      - October 12, 1863 - October 29, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 10)
        Civil War; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends; New York State Agricultural Rooms.
        October 12, 1863. M.B. Wood to Ezra Cornell describing a battle.
        October 18, 1863. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing life in a convalescent hospital in Illinois.
        Millspaugh, John H.; Wood, M.B.; Wood, O.S.; Cornell, John H.; Cornell, D.B.
      - November 2, 1863 - November 19, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 11)
        New York State Legislature: legislation.
        Robertson, M.O.; Wood, O.S.; Cornell, John W.; Sibley, Hiram; Cornell, John H.; Pew, W.P.
      - November 20, 1863 - December 11, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 12)
        New York State Legislature; agriculture; sheep; Forest Park farm; New York State canals.
        November 29, 1863. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing life in a convalescent hospital in Illinois.
        Curtiss, George; Pew, W.P.; Robertson, M.O.; Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, D.B.; Wood, O.S.
      - December 12, 1863 - December 26, 1863 (Box 23, Folder 13)
        Agriculture; New York State Legislature; New York State canals; cattle; Western Union Telegraph Company.
        Speed, J.J.; Ingersoll, Charles; Barnard, D.R.; Chester, E.W.; Cornell, Paul J.; Cornell, Ezra E.
      - December 28, 1863 - January 9, 1864 (Box 23, Folder 14)
        New York State Legislature: legislation; real estate; Civil War; Western Union Telegraph Company: stock; New York State Agricultural College (Ovid); Cornell Public Library; New York State canals; Cascadilla Institute; People's College.
        December 31, 1863. Benjamin Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing camp life and re-enlistments.
        January 6, 1864. J.P.S. Briant to Ezra Cornell:
        "The accompanying Pistol and ammunition was captured from a Rebel officer at the Storming of 'St. Mary's Hights,' Fredericksburgh?. As these mementos of the 'Slave Holders Rebellion' will be prized in after times, I take pleasure in placing them in your hands for presentation to the Farmers Club of Tompkins County for preservation."
        Cornell, Benjamin; Cartwright, Robert; Finch, F.M.; Greeley, Horace.
      - January 10, 1864 - January 17, 1864 (Box 23, Folder 15)
        New York State Legislature: legislation; New York State canals; Western Union Telegraph Company: stock; Forest Park farm; Cascadilla Institute; Ezra Cornell's will; Family correspondence; Ithaca Savings Bank.
        January 13, 1864. Ezra Cornell to F.M. Finch:
        "I have five children, it would not benefit them to give them more than $100,000 each, thus less than half is disposed of?The Library will probably absorb $60,000, but supposing it to go to $75,000. What shall I do with the balance? I hope to do much good with it, but I really don't know how to dispose of it in a will so as to do the good with it that I should desire to do."
        January 15, 1864. F.M. Finch to Ezra Cornell:
        "Your remarks with reference to a will have staggered me. Your reflections have carried you into a region where mine had not entered."
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Franklin C.; Finch, F.M.; Curtiss, George; Smith, F.O.J.
      - January 18, 1864 - January 24, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; Cornell Public Library; Ezra Cornell's will; Cascadilla Institute; Ladies Aid Society; Civil War; Ezra Cornell's charitable contributions; Family correspondence; New York State Legislature: legislation.
        Finch, F.M.; Speed, J.J.; Wood, Phebe; Cornell, O.H. Perry; Cornell, E.B.
      - January 25, 1864 - February 1, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 2)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents; Forest Park farm; Civil War; gun stock; Agriculture; New York State canals; Cornell Public Library.
        January 30, 1864. William Glenny letter describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Chester, E.W.; Glenny, William; Cornell, John H.
      - February 2, 1864 - February 8, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        New York State Agricultural survey; agriculture; Wisconsin lands; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents; Civil War; New York State canals; Forest Park farm.
        February 6, 8, 1864. William Glenny letters describing life and Army politics in camp in Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Parker, Amasa J.; Finch, F.M.; Cornell, O.H. Perry; Wood, W. Irving.
      - February 9, 1864 - February 17, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 4)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents; New York State canals; Cornell Public Library; Land Grant Act; People's College; Agriculture; Cayuga Lake.
        February 11, 1864. Douglass Boardman to Ezra Cornell describing a tableaux theatrical presentation in Ithaca.
        February 14, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from convalescent hospital where he is a nurse:
        "If I were doing any thing to help crush the rebellion I would not murmer, but to have been shot in the way I was, and that too within three minutes after getting in sight of the Devils for the first time, and then not being premitted to go back to the field when I could actualy do more duty than four such men as they have been sending back who have recovered (or rather partialy recovered) from the various ills contracted in camp life, I tell you it is rather chilling."
        Pew, W.P.; Wood, M.B.; Boardman, Douglass; Glenny, William; Spaulding, Henry C.; Wells, Henry; Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, D.B.
      - February 18, 1864 - February 24, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 5)
        Civil War; Cornell family genealogy and history; New York State canals; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents.
        February 18, 22, 24, 1864. William Glenny letters describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Wood, M.B.; Pew, W.P.; Beebe, Jessie C.; Boardman, Douglass.
      - February 25, 1864 - February 29, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        New York State canals; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; Forest Park farm; Danby farm; Cornell family genealogy and history; cattle; sheep; agriculture.
        February 26, 1864. William Glenny letter describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        February 28, 1864. Franklin C. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "Perry moved last week his stock that he left to danby looks hard I don't think I ever saw a lot of calves that looked worse than his do?"
        Pew, W.P.; Cornell, John H.; Sibley, Hiram; Cornell, Franklin C.; Millspaugh, John H.
      - March 1, 1864 - March 11, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 7)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents; Civil War.
        March 3, 10, 1864. William Glenny letters describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Spaulding, Henry C.; Sibley, Hiram; Wood, Phebe; Chester, E.W.; Glenny, William.
      - March 12, 1864 - March 19, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 8)
        New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; Cornell Public Library; Agriculture; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; New York State canals.
        March 12, 1864. William Glenny letter describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Cornell, E.B.; Pew, W.P.; Glenny, William.
      - March 21, 1864 - March 29, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 9)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; Cascadilla Place; Saratoga Race Course; New York State Legislature: legislation; Ezra Cornell's donation to Ithaca band; New York State Agricultural College (Ovid).
        March 21, 1864. William Glenny letter describing life and Army politics in camp near Germania Ford, Virginia.
        Nivison, S.S.; Curtiss, George; Speed, J.J.; Glenny, William.
      - March 30, 1864 - April 12, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 10)
        Telegraph industry: western lines; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; Steam cultivation; Wisconsin lands; national legislation; Cornelian Band (Ithaca); New York State canals.
        Sibley, Hiram; Wood, M.B.; Lee, W.; Beebe, A.; Speed, J.J.; Beebe, Jessie C.
      - April 13, 1864 - April 23, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 11)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock, Russian stock; New York State Legislature: legislation, letters from constituents and others; national legislation.
        April 13, 1864. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "From present appearances there will be no lack of capital to carry the thing through and I do hope you will not allow yourself to get into a position which will cause you the least uneasiness financially. You have worked hard and have secured a fortune?I really hope you will conclude to make your subn. $300,000 instead of $500,00."
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Sage, H.W.; Sibley, Hiram; Speed, J.J.
      - April 24, 1864 - May 6, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 12)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends; Russian Telegraph; New York State Agricultural Rooms; New York State Legislature: legislation; Civil War; national legislation; Cornell family genealogy and history; Ithaca Gun Company.
        April 26, 1864. W. Irving Wood to Ezra Cornell from camp near Alexandria, Virginia:
        "We left Annapolis at 6 A.M. the 23rd inst. we passed through Washington at noon yesterday & was reviewed by Genl. Burnside & the President as we passed, and we made a good appearance but it was very hard work after marching for two days & the night before we laid out through a drenching ravine & had marched 10 miles through the mud besides fording a stream that morning. Quite a number of men died yesterday on the road. Our corps now has 4 divisions the forth is of colored troops."
        DeRuyter; Ithaca.
        Sibley, Hiram; Wood, W. Irving; Chester, E.W.; Barnard, Reuben; Selkreg, J.H.
      - May 7, 1864 - May 20, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 13)
        Steam cultivation; New York Steam Agriculture Company; telegraph industry; Western Union Telegraph Company: dividends, stock; national legislation.
        May 13, 1864. Petition by members of New York State Senate to Secretary of War Edwin Stanton:
        "The undersigned respectfully request a pass for Hon. Ezra Cornell to go within the lines of our Army to render assistance to the wounded."
        May 18, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "I am going out into the State of Missouri recruiting for the 29th Ill. Colored Regt."
        May 20, 1864. John W. Brown to Ezra Cornell describing at length activities in and battles of the Union Army.
        Selkreg, J.H.; Sibley, Hiram; Cornell, D.B.; Brown, John W.
      - May 21, 1864 - June 4, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 14)
        Civil War; Cornell family genealogy and history; steam cultivator; Russian stock.
        May 21, 1864. W. Irving Wood to Ezra Cornell describing battles near Spottsylvania.
        May 29, 1864. John W. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from New Orleans describing his capture and wounding in a war skirmish:
        "Probley you have sean the account of the capchur of the Gun Boat Signal No. 8 the one that I was on."
        Wood, W. Irving; Wright, Avis; Sibley, Hiram; Robinson, R.R.; Chester, E.W.; Cornell, John W.; Speed, J.J.; Wood, O.S.; Fenton, Reuben.
      - June 5, 1864 - June 22, 1864 (Box 24, Folder 15)
        Agriculture; Russian stock; Ezra Cornell's Wisconsin lands; Civil War: colored regiments.
        Chester, E.W.; Balch, G.W.; Cornell, D.B.; Pierpont, J.E.; Willers, D.
      - June 23, 1864 - July 19, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        Cattle; Montezuma Swamp; New York State Legislature; Massachusetts "cattle plague"; New York State Agricultural Society; telegraph business correspondence: Russian Telegraph stock; Western Union Company: stocks.
        June 25, 1864. Mrs. Paul Cornell (Keturah M.) to Ezra Cornell from Portsmouth, N.C. describing her losses in the war.
        July 11, 1864. Paul J. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from Portsmouth, N.C. requesting loan from Ezra Cornell to reestablish himself in business in the South, possibly by speculating in cotton.
        July 19, 1864. John W. Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing conditions in a naval hospital in Chelsea, Mass.
        Palmer, O.H.; Spalding, Henry C.; Hopkins, P.A.; Cornell, Paul J.; Chester, E.W.; Cornell, J.W.; Cornell, Keturah.
      - July 20, 1864 - August 9, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        Cattle; Civil War; Cornell Public Library (workers' strike); telegraph business correspondence: Ithaca Telegraph Company; offer of natural history collection; steam agricultural machinery; New York State canals.
        July 20, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from camp near Memphis, Tenn.:
        "My health is very good & the condition of my jaw's as such that I can eat any rations but hard tack, & I much prefer field to Hospital duty."
        July 20, August 1, 1864. J.H. Millspaugh to Ezra Cornell requesting his assistance in starting a photography studio in Ithaca, and making use of a room in the library building.
        July 23, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from camp near Memphis, Tenn. requesting his assistance in obtaining a commission in the Veteran Reserve Corps.
        July 24, 1864. John G. Apgar to Ezra Cornell informing him of the death of his nephew W. Irving Wood from his wound received in battle:
        "He was buried on Arlington Hights on the farm formeraly owned by Gen. R. E. Lee at present commanding the Rebel Army his and all other graves are properly marked and a record kept so that if the friends wish to they can remove the body in the fall?"
        July 28, August 3, 1864. Albert H. Chace to Ezra Cornell requesting advise and aid in opening an upholstery business.
        Cornell, D.B.; Millspaugh, J.H.; Beebe, Alvah; Chester, E.W.; Wood, W. Irving; Apgar, J.G.; Chace, Albert H.; Jewett, E.; Boardman, Douglass; Palmer, O.H.; Cornell, E.B.; Lee, W.; Lummis, W.
      - August 10, 1864 - read August 31, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        New York State canals; offer of natural history collections; steam agricultural machinery; telegraph business correspondence: stock; cattle; Cornell Public Library.
        August 11, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from Camp at St. Charles, Ark.
        August 27, 1864. B. Cassedy of the Office of the Commissioners of Emigration to Ezra Cornell concerning laborers for the building of the library.
        Howell, R.; Cornell, D.B.; Adams, W.H.; Jewett, E.; Lummis, W.; Lee, W.; Cornell, John H.
      - September 1, 1864 - September 18, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 4)
        New York State Agricultural Company; Western Union Telegraph Company; New York State Agricultural College (Ovid); telegraph business correspondence: inventions; steam agricultural machinery.
        September 5, 1864. C.S. Lozier, M.D. to Ezra Cornell concerning a scholarship to the New York Medical College for Women.
        Johnson, B.P.; Palmer, O.H.; Beebe, Alvah; Lozier, C.S., M.D.; Hawley, G.P.; Cornell, John H.; Lee, W.; Jewett, E.; Cornell, J.W.
      - September 20, 1864 - October 7, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 5)
        Cattle; New York State Agricultural College; real estate (Brooklyn); Cornell Public Library; Smith versus Cornell.
        October 3, 1864. "Ella" in New Hampshire to Ezra Cornell:
        "?I am gifted with what my teachers say, an uncommonly beautiful voice for singing, and being passionately fond of music, I have tried hard to get the means to purchase me an instrument, a Melodeon, is what I have always wished for. My parents have not the means to help me, and having no one else in this wide world to ask assistance of, it gave me encouragement to ask you, an entire stranger, when I read of your generosity. O! kind Sir, if you will enclose me one hundred dollars?"
        October 7, 1864. Henry A. Ward to Ezra Cornell describing various fossils he is interested in selling.
        Bush, Isaac L.; Joy, Arad; Lee, W.; Finch, F.M.; Nichols & Brown; Allen, A.B.; Cornell, J.W.; Shaw, O.F.; Chester, E.W.; Ward, Henry A.
      - October 8, 1864 - October 22, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 6)
        New York State Agricultural College; family correspondence.
        Valk, Lawrence B.; Joy, Arad; Cornell, Keturah; Cornell, J.W.; Wood, Phebe; Chace, Eunice; Johnson, B.P.; Allen, A.B.; Cornell, John H.; Raplee, S.S; Robertson, Mary C.; Lee, W.
      - October 26, 1864 - November 17, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 7)
        Western Union Telegraph Company: stocks and bonds; New York Medical College for Women.
        October 24, 1864. P. J. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from Portsmouth, N.C. describing his life and business ventures in the South.
        October 28, 1864. Wilbur F. Crummer to Ezra Cornell from Pleasant Valley, Ill.:
        "I see you have given $50,000 for a public Library to be formed in Ithica N.Y. now can you give a poor wounded invalid soldier, who is closely confined to the house, some few books or magazines to read through the coming winter? I love to read, but am to poor to buy the works I should like to read. The hours pass off slowly when I have nothing to read?the smallest favor will be thankfully received."
        Cornell, Paul J.; Chace, Eunice; Palmer, O.H.; Crummer, W.F.; Lozier, C.S.; Porter, Ira; Chace, Baylus; Rowell, Mary; Wood, O.S.
      - November 18, 1864 - December 11, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 8)
        Civil War; re-election of Lincoln; sheep; cattle; real estate; New York State Legislature; telegraph business correspondence.
        November 18, 1864. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell from camp at St. Louis, Mo. describing marches and his interest in purchasing farmlands near Sedalia, Mo.
        December 16, 1864. Amos Brown to Ezra Cornell from Havana discussing the People's College and asking Ezra Cornell that he consider building his college in Havana or Ovid.
        Legg, Louis P.; Cornell, D.B.; Ingersoll, Henry; Bush, I.L.; Millspaugh, J.H.; Wood, M.B.; Brown, Amos; Porter, Ira.
      - December 12, 1864 - December 31, 1864 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence; location of New York State Agricultural College, possible relocation to Ithaca; Albany Agricultural Works; Cornell University.
        December 17, 1864. W.F. Crummer to Ezra Cornell from Pleasant Valley, Illinois: